Finding Aid for William H. Withington Papers [microform], 1853-1909
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William H. Withington papers [microform] 1853-1909
Withington, William Herbert, 1835-1903.
2 microfilm rolls
Civil War officer, banker, Republican State Representative and Senator from Jackson, Michigan. Correspondence, special orders, notes, business papers, and miscellaneous items, primarily relating to his Civil War service as Colonel of the Seventeenth Michigan Infantry, and to a possible appointment to the U.S. Senate in 1894; also notes on the management of the Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company, 1895-1903, diary of a European trip, 1897, and photographs.
86340 mf323, mf324
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These materials were acquired in 1951 from Col. Winthrop Withington [Donor no. 2837 ].
The collection is open for research.
Originals of the collection are available. Access is restricted to the microfilm except for non-microfilmed portions or with special permission.
William Herbert Withington was born in Dorchester, Massachusetts, on February 1, 1835. He received his education in Boston and Andover, and then began his career in business. In 1857 he joined the firm of Pinney & Lamson, agricultural implement manufacturers, to oversee their contract for prison labor in Jackson, Michigan. Withington soon had the opportunity to acquire the business from his previous employers, and co-founded Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company.
In May 1861 Withington joined the Michigan Infantry Regiment, 1st, as a captain of Company B, the Jackson Greys. In July 1861 the 1st Michigan was deeply involved in the first Battle of Bull Run at Manassas, Virginia. Several of the company were cut off from Union forces, and although Withington was reported as dead, he was among those taken as a prisoner of war during the battle. His release was negotiated as part of a prisoner exchange in January 1862. He was commissioned colonel of the newly formed 17th Michigan Infantry in August 1862, and was discharged from the army in March 1863. In 1865 he was brevetted brigadier general of the U. S. Volunteers for his actions in the battles of South Mountain and Antietam. He remained active in the State Militia until 1883, and served on committees for Civil War memorials.
Following his discharge, Withington returned to management of his company in Jackson, Michigan. A Republican, he served in the Michigan State Legislature as Representative of Jackson County, 1873-1874, and as Senator of the Sixth District, 1891-1892. In 1894 he made an unsuccessful bid to be appointed to a vacant seat in the U.S. Senate. Gen. William H. Withington died on June 27, 1903.
The papers of William H. Withington consist of correspondence, special orders, notes, and miscellaneous items relating to his Civil War service as Colonel of the Seventeenth Michigan Infantry; business records of the Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company, correspondence and other material concerning his political career as Republican state legislator and state senator.
This collection is divided into four series: Civil War Activities, Personal Papers, Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company Records, all of which are arranged chronologically, and Newspaper Clippings.
Subjects:
Business records.; Europe--Description and travel.; Grand Army of the Republic.; Jackson (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 1st (1861). Company B.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 17th (1862-1865); United States. Congress. Senate.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Voyages and travels.; Withington, William Herbert, 1835-1903.; Withington and Cooley Manufacturing Company.
Contributors - Mixed Materials
Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Bagley, John Judson, 1832-1881.; Baker, Benjamin B., b. 1840.; Bevier, Jonathan.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Blair, Sarah Ford.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Jones, John, 1818-1887.; Luce, Constant.; Lyon, G. Collins.; Newman, George S.; Philips, Delos, 1840-1887.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Rath, Christian, 1832-1920.; Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.; Trowbridge, Rowland E., 1821-1881.; Tyler, John, 1841-1889.; Winegar, William, b. 1827.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Battlefields--Virginia.; Camp Crosswell (Mich.); Michigan. State Troops (1862-1893); Military camps.; Soldiers--American.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 1st (1861). Company B.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Withington, William Herbert, 1835-1903.
Contributors - Visual Materials
Brady, Mathew B., 1823 (ca.)-1896.
Genre/Form:
Account books.; Diaries.; Photographs.
- Civil War Activities
  Of special note in the Civil War Activities series is an 1861 diary in which Withington records events of his P.O.W. internment, as well as a "Remembrance as P.O.W." which was written later. Other materials in this series include correspondence, of which only a few are penned by Withington; expense journals kept by Withington, both military and personal; photographs; and papers regarding Withington's extensive post-war activities with the Grand Army of the Republic and Civil War memorials.
  - Diary 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1861 (Reel 1)
    - 1862 (Reel 1)
    - 1863 (Reel 1)
    - 1864 (Reel 1)
  - Expense Journals
    - Military 1861 (Reel 1)
    - Personal
      - 1860-1861 (Reel 1)
        Includes drafts of speeches/articles
      - 1863 (Reel 1)
  - Remembrance as P.O.W., July 1861-January 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Miscellanea 1861-1863 (Reel 1)
  - Photographs (Reel 1)
    Group portrait of Withington and others taken prisoner at the first battle of Bull Run; photograph by Mathew Brady of a house near Bull Run battlefield; and photographs of an encampment of the Michigan State Troops; and miscellaneous portraits.
  - Post-war Activities
    - Grand Army of the Republic and Memorial Hall Committee 1892-1893 (Reel 1)
    - War Memorial Work 1894-1898 (Reel 1)
    - "The First Call of the Civil War: Personal Recollections of Michigan's Response" read by Gen. W. H. Withington 1897 (Reel 1)
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers series are post-1866, and are largely correspondence and other materials from Withington's political activities. Correspondents include: Russell A. Alger, John J. Bagley, Benjamin B. Baker, Jonathan Bevier, Austin Blair, Mrs. Austin Blair, Julius C. Burrows, John Jones, Constant Luce, G. Collins Lyon, George S. Newman, Delos Philips, Hazen S. Pingree, Christian Rath, John T. Rich, Rowland E. Trowbridge, and John Tyler.
  - Correspondence and Other Papers 1866-1890 (Reel 1)
  - Michigan State Senate 1891-1892 (Reel 1)
  - Attempted U.S. Senate Appointment May 1894 (Reel 1)
  - Withington's Views on Money Issue 1896 (Reel 1)
  - Miscellanea 1859-1909, undated (Reel 1)
- Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company Records
  The majority of the Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company Records series consists of 26 annual journals of personal business expenses kept by Withington. There are also three volumes of company accounts and ledgers.
  - Personal Expense Journals
    Not microfilmed
    - 1853-1878, 10 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1879-1902, 16 volumes (Box 1)
  - Accounts 1857-1858 (Reel 1)
  - Business Journal 1889-1903 (Reel 1)
  - Ledger 1894-1903 (Reel 1)
  - Miscellanea 1859-1902 (Reel 1)
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings series are scrapbooks compiled by Withington's wife, Julia. The bulk of these clippings document the Civil War activities, particularly of Michigan regiments, and some post-Civil War memorial activities and miscellaneous. Many clippings are without notations regarding date or source, and do not appear to be in chronological order. The final scrapbook contains clippings and ephemera about Withington's death.
  - 1861 (Reel 2)
  - 1861-1862, 2 volumes (Reel 2)
  - 1862-1863 (Reel 2)
    Copies of clippings made from Accounts 1857-1858 volume in Withington & Cooley Manufacturing Company Records series
  - 1861-1902 (Reel 2)
  - 1881-1990 (Reel 2)
  - June-August, 1903 (Reel 2)
    re death of W. H. Withington